Welcome to the Truth Over Comfort Show.
Today's returning guest is John Kiryaku,
who was in the CIA for many years and
eventually went on to blow the whistle
on the CI CIA torture program. I
previously had him on the show to
discuss that. Um, the types of
techniques the CIA would use, the black
sites and everything in between. Um, I
thought this time we could just have
more of a general chat, as I was saying
before, you know, these subjects you've
spoken about over and over and over. And
so I thought it just be a good idea to
to speak about stuff going on in the
world, but other general topics too,
just to see your personal insight being
within the CIA and the government for
that many years and just yourself as
well. Um, but it's great to have you on
again, John. How you doing? Thanks for
uh thanks for the invitation, Louie. My
pleasure. Yeah. No, I appreciate your
time. I know you're a busy man going
around doing the podcast as hopefully
everyone's been watching. recommend uh
all of the recent um long form podcast.
You've done a lot of good uh information
in there. So, just um to to jump into
one subject actually just touching on
within your career in the CIA uh and
working in counter terrorism. Um, you
know, the war on terror is still
fluctuating on and off and there's still
a lot of fear um about the risks of
terrorism and it going on in the Middle
East and just generally in America and
and the UK. Um, people have a lot of
different ideas about the causes of
terrorism. You know, the classic kind of
cliche joke line of George Bush about
they hate us for our freedoms, which I
don't know how many people really
believe that. Um, and then you have
people who believe, you know, it's an
issue not just with radical Islam, but
just Muslims in general, they're a
violent um, religion. And then there's a
lot of other ideas and stuff that gets
left out, but within the CIA and with
the intel reports you get, what are the
causes of terrorism? Um, do they expel a
different view when they speak to the
public to the information you get for
the reasons for certain attacks? What
what is some of the causes of terrorism
in your professional view? I I think
that I've nailed this down, at least in
my own mind. Um
um number
one, lack of access to
education. Number two is lack of
economic development.
And I'll tell you, I got that straight
from the horse's mouth when I was the
the chief of CIA counterterrorism
operations in Pakistan.
Um, we captured so many al-Qaeda
fighters. I say fighters like low-level
grunts, 18, 19, 20 years old, and they
all told exactly the same story. They
said that they were some from some
isolated village in their home country.
They had um uh they didn't know how to
read and write. They had no uh job
skills and they wanted to get married.
But what man would want his daughter to
marry a young man who can't read and
can't write and doesn't have any skills
and has no prospects for employment? So
the local imam went up to them and said,
"You don't want to stay in this this
isolated village. you should go to
Afghanistan and make jihad against the
Americans. And if you do that, we'll pay
you $300 a month. And if you're martyed,
we'll give your parents a $500 martyrdom
bonus. Well, they had nothing else to
lose. They couldn't find the United
States on a map. They didn't know
anything about American foreign policy.
They were just poor and and and
uneducated and unskilled.
So, for the most part, I'm going to say,
you know,
80% would never have turned to
terrorism. Probably didn't even realize
they were involved in
terrorism. Um, they wouldn't have turned
to terrorism had they had educations and
job opportunities. The for the other
20%, I really believe that their
decision to turn to terrorism was a
response to US foreign policy. You know,
several several al-Qaeda fighters,
mid-level al-Qaeda fighters, said that
they had no problem with the United
States until they saw video of Israeli
soldiers with their boots on the necks
of Palestinian
women and they blamed the United States
for its blind support of Israel. So, it
was our foreign policy. I really believe
that if we had a more balanced foreign
policy and we really did make use of
foreign aid to encourage economic
development with no strings attached, we
wouldn't have these problems that we
have.
Yeah. Know, I think, you know, I didn't
mention it before, but foreign policy is
definitely, you know, got to be a
motivating factor. you hear it time and
time again after the attack a little bit
later normally, you know, there it was a
response to the Iraq war, Afghanistan or
or Israel. Um, so just, you know, put
out you don't think there's anything to
do with particularly Muslims in their
religion. It's more, you know, those
seem to be the groups of people
constantly attacked in the Middle East.
It's not that Muslims are a violent
religion. It happens that these people
in Iraq, Afghanistan, Syria. Oh, no, no.
I've I've studied Islam. I have a degree
in in uh Middle Eastern studies with a
focus on Islamic theology. I studied
under some of the most important uh
Muslim scholars in the West and uh and
served most of my adult life in the
Middle East. Uh I've read the Quran.
This is
not a religion of of hate or a religion
of violence any more than Christianity
is a religion of hate or a religion of
violence. Of course, there are going to
be extremists on all sides. There are.
We see them every day in the news. But,
uh, no. In terms of of Islam being a
violent religion, no, I've never
believed that.
Yeah. I mean, you've got what, over two
billion Muslims around the world, mostly
peaceful. You take that number, there's
not too many attacks. I mean, you have,
say, you know, a Christian American who
goes to the war in the Middle East in
Iraq. No one's necessarily saying it
because he's a Christian. You know, it's
just the rules aren't really played for
both sides, right? You know, people
like, oh, why don't Jews or Hindus, why
are they not, you know, doing terrorist
attacks? It's normally because we're not
attacking those people, you know, I
mean, why would why would they attack
us? There's no reason to. So within the
CIA in your position knowing some of the
motivation is foreign policy
specifically you know US NATO Israeli
foreign policy what what do the kind of
the people the the higherups in in the
chain at the CIA and government think
about that? Do they know that and
they're like it's just blowback like
that's just the price to pay because
when it gets put out to the public it's
it's you always push it away from
foreign policy. It's never about that.
It's never about the war in Libya. This
is the problem with the CIA being
um not being a policy um agency. The the
CIA is tasked with um well the the the
job of a CIA officer is very simple. It
is to recruit spies to steal secrets and
then to analyze those secrets to provide
the policy makers with the best
information to make policy. Foreign
policy is made at the White House
essentially. It's carried out by the
State Department, but it's made at the
White House. And the White House is
always a political entity. As a
political entity, it is it is subject to
outside pressure. Outside pressure by
the best funded organizations. And
arguably the best funded organization is
going to be Apac, the Israel lobby, and
supporters of Apac and and supporters of
of uh think tanks that are supportive of
Israel. And so the Israelis have
a a greatly
outsized influence on American foreign
policy. They spend their money very
smartly. they spend it uh or Apac spends
it supporting pro-Israel congressional
candidates to the point
where not
only will you be accused of being
anti-semitic if you're not
Zionist, you're now accused of being
anti-Semitic if you're not a supporter
of Benjamin Netanyahu as a
person. That is so
outrageous that I can't even believe
we've gotten to this point. But this is
indeed the point we've gotten to. It's
funny too because when you look back in
modern American history,
um that wasn't the case until
1969. In 1969, Richard Nixon made a
major policy decision and that was to
protect Israel no matter what. No
questions asked. And that's when Apac
Apac became a a political force to be
reckoned with in the United States. It
wasn't always this way. It's been this
way since 1969.
Yeah. know just to for people I'd
recommend watching some of the recent
podcasts you did um as I know you go
into about um kind of the CIA's view
about Israel and you tell that story
about um kind of diplomats who went
there and Israel kind of messed with
them and their house and breakin to know
like we you know we're messing with you
we can end up chopping off was it the
dog's tail so the dog's tail yeah I
won't make you go into that because I
know you told it many times I recommend
people go into that I'll put it up on
the on the screen how this is behind the
scenes with, you know, the f the
frenemies kind of thing that's going on.
You already started to say there were
red lights. You know, you're told that
day one. It's like you see China, you
see Russia, you see Israel as like spy
threats or whatever. That's right. So
people at CIA, I would
imagine have a lovehate relationship
here. Is that fair to say? Uh, it's
mostly just a hate relationship.
I never met anybody at the CIA who was
pro-Israel. Never. Not one. Not a single
person.
No. No. Not a single person. And it's
because they make it so hard to like
them. You know, if we're supposed to be
their best friends, we have this special
relationship. Well, I I'll tell you the
same the same story I told Danny Jones.
I worked with this guy for years and he
married a woman in the office. Really
terrific people. Both of them. Terrific
people. And when I was going out to
Bahrain uh on my rotation to the state
department, the wife was going out to
Jerusalem because she got the same
rotation to the state department. So
because she had worked with the Israelis
for many years, uh the station decided
to declare the two of them to the
Israelis. So they they land and they go
straight to Mossad and the chief said,
"These are my officers. She's on
rotation to the State Department and
he's just going to study Arabic at the
University of Tel Aviv." Yeah. Right. No
harm. Uhhuh. So, they're there for a
little while. They go to a party at the
ambassador's residence and they come
home and all of their living room
furniture had been rearranged. And
they're like, you know, not cool. But
this is what the Israelis do. They break
in the house. They rearrange all your
furniture just to say, "Ha, [__] you. We
can do anything we want." So, they're
there working. Months pass. They're
having a good time. They go to uh the
ambassador's Christmas party. Now
they're living in Jerusalem. The embassy
at the time was in Tel Aviv and so it's
about a 30 or 40 minute drive to get
from one city to the other. They come
home at the end of the party and people
had taken shits in all of their toilets
in their house. Every toilet had had
[__] in it. You know, not cool. They're
not doing anything. They're not working
against the Israelis. They're just doing
normal stuff. He's studying Arabic.
she's just in the the embassy's uh you
know economic section or whatever. And
um and then when their tour was over,
two-year tour, the ambassador threw a
going away party for them, which is a
normal thing. And they get back to the
house, and the dog is under the dining
room table whimpering because somebody
had cut the dog's tail off and they
wrapped it with gauze and with medical
tape. Now, why why would you do
something like that? What do you hope to
gain except to make us hate you? You
know, if you're trying to win friends
and influence people, that's really not
the way you you're going to want to go.
So, now here are these people who, if
anything, were, you know, moderately
supportive of the Israelis who came home
only with bitterness and hatred toward
the Israelis for this harassment that
lasted for two years. Why? Why would you
do that? What do you hope to accomplish?
Do you ever think that some of that is
people who want you to think it's them?
I'm steel manning it, but in a place
like Israel though, there's nobody else
sophisticated enough to do something
like that. Um, so just going back to
what you said there about Israel. Um,
people probably don't really associate
it with causing terror. Can you just
explain what you mean by the blowback of
our support for Israel? Uh do you have
any examples within your time or or
beyond because you know the support was
always strong there but now you know we
have the internet and the current war.
Sure. You know we the United States
purports to be uh not just a country
that supports human rights but the
greatest supporter of human rights in
the world. That's just simply not true.
Uh we completely turn a blind eye to
human rights in Israel. Um, I was
speaking just recently in the last
couple of weeks with a with a an Israeli
human rights attorney, an Israeli human
rights attorney who told me that since
uh the conflict in Gaza began, um,
thousands and thousands of Palestinians
have been scooped up and placed in
Israeli prisons without being charged
with a crime. Okay, that's a human
rights violation. But even worse,
they're not permitted to
speak. And I mean like at all for any
reason. They're not permitted to speak.
And over the last six months or so,
they're not permitted to walk inside
prisons. They have to go from point A to
point B on their hands and knees. Now
we're seeing prisoners, Palestinian
prisoners, being released from Israeli
prisons, and they look like death camp
survivors, gaunt, underfed,
malnourished.
This this is it's a clear human rights
violation and Israel is a first world
country. It's not like they don't have
enough food to go around. This was a
policy decision to not provide prisoners
with food. So you're This is a thing
that I hate about the American media too
is they always talk about
um Israeli hostages and Palestinian
detaininees. What's the difference
between the two? the the Palestinians
are as much hostages as the Israelis
being held by Hamas are
hostages. And believe me, I'm
anti-Hamas. I believe Hamas is a
terrorist organization. But I like to
think that I understand why it has come
to the four as a group. You can only
suppress or oppress a people for so long
before they're finally going to react.
And we saw the reaction.
Why is it do you think Israel treats the
the prisoners so badly and you know
because people would argue you know
these people are terrorists or you know
similar to the US where they think
someone's a terrorist or they think
they're going to stop terrorist acts and
these people kind of get caught up in it
or is it something different to the US
because there is the element of kind of
the dehumanization of of Palestinians to
Israelis where Muslims were dehumanized
in the war on terror but not it's not
the same because they're neighbors or
within each other. So why do you think
they do treat them so poorly? I think
that it's because official Israeli
policy is to is to encourage all
Palestinians to leave Palestine. You
know, Donald Trump was not joking when
he said he wanted to develop Gaza into
beachfront, you know, resort real estate
that would be better than Monte Carlo.
He said, "You can only do that if there
are no Palestinians living there." And I
really believe that that's the goal. You
know, we're seeing we're seeing
unprecedented Israeli settlements in uh
in the West Bank right now. And it's
because the world's attention is
diverted. It's on it's on Gaza. Well,
people are dying every day in the West
Bank, and more and more Palestinian land
is being stolen in the West Bank. And
it's because official Israeli policy is
to throw everybody out. The ones that
you kill, you kill. The ones that you
don't kill, get them to leave. And so we
know, for example, that the United
States, the Trump administration has
spoken to the governments of Jordan,
Egypt, Saudi Arabia, Albania, Indonesia
about just taking all
Palestinians and and resettling them in
their countries. Of course, that's
that's it actually meets the legal
definition of of a genocide. Uh but
nobody seems to really care very much
about that. And here in the United
States, in in um well, not just in the
United States, also in Canada, in
synagogues around both countries,
they're having what they call um real
estate seminars following Shabbat
services. They're not real estate
seminars. their um their seminars on how
to get your name on a on a list to take
possession of stolen Palestinian land if
you want to be a settler in the West
Bank or Gaza. That's that's a war crime.
You can't do that. But the Israelis are
doing it and the American and Canadian
governments are allowing them to do it.
Yeah, I think they also speaking to
Somalia and Sudan as well or Somalia
land as well. Um, and yeah, I mean
there's that clip that went around a
while back um of that American, he's
speaking American and he's in the West
Bank and he goes to that house and he's
like, you know, give me a house. They're
like, no, no, like we're not giving.
He's like, you know, if I don't take it,
someone else will. It's not my fault.
Just, you know, it's not my fault I
didn't do it. And they're like, no, but
you're trying to sell my house. He's
like, well, if I don't, someone else
someone else will. You know, if me being
in England, if I was Jewish, I'm not. I
could literally just fly, you know, go
over to Israel, go to the West Bank and
steal someone's house and probably be
supported by the army and and no
consequence. It's crazy. And and if they
put up a a fight, um then they're shot
or their their olive trees are
bulldozed, their homes are bulldozed,
and they end up living in tents or in
caves, and the Israelis hope that
eventually they'll just get tired and
leave.
Yeah. And it's crazy like you was
speaking before about anti-semitism. If
you say, you know, I don't think
Israelis should steal Palestinian hand
houses in the West Bank, no one would
go, oh, that's anti anti-semitic. But,
you know, now it is. And and even going
back to the anti-semitism there. Even if
you're I've heard, you know, like Jewish
people at crowds at rallies where
they're, you know, Jews for Palestine.
Um, they're called like self-hating
Jews. Um, they're called traitors.
people like threatening them and
screaming at them. And there's articles
of people writing this like this
self-paying Jew thing and just, you
know, like you don't have to be for
Israel if you're a Jew and because you
and you don't have to be um Jewish to be
a Zionist. As we can see, many people
support the the existence of Israel. But
um yeah, it's a a bizarre um situation.
just going just over uh the border to
Syria within the discussion of
terrorism. What do you make of HCS?
Because, you know, before I'd have
people on and speak about Syria and you
talk about, you know, did we purposely,
you know, um was we directly arming
al-Qaeda and ISIS or was it indirectly
or did arms fall into them or was it
through now with HTS it's it's like I
don't know now you know the UK have
visited there the EU Germany you know
they just he just they went to the world
economic forum um so it went from like
was it direct to now like was it um
David Miller? He's a he was a university
professor who was fired um for being
anti-Zionist. Um and he put out a tweet
and he was like, "I wonder how long
until um Syria HTS regime is at the
World Economic Forum." It was like a
month. Yeah, you're exactly right. You
know, this is a this is a an American
foreign policy with which I have a very
serious problem.
Uh,
al-Qaeda attacked the United States on
September 11th, 2001 and killed 3,000
people in one morning. 3,000 people. I
was one of many, many people who
dedicated my life to working against
al-Qaeda to to locating al-Qaeda leaders
and killing them.
ISIS was formed by a faction of al-Qaeda
that believed that al-Qaeda wasn't
radical
enough and and it slaughtered civilians
in Iraq and Syria and
elsewhere. And that's who the US decided
to throw its lot in with. So they
changed their
names, al-Qaeda, the Nusra front,
whatever it is, they're terrorists who
meant us
harm. But we convinced ourselves that
Bashar al-Assad was so evil that he had
to be overthrown at all costs. My po my
position all along was that whether you
like Bashar al-Assad or not, he was the
only thing standing between the
Christian community in Syria and utter
annihilation. And so that's now what
we're seeing. We've gotten into bed with
al-Qaeda, regardless of what name they
happen to be using today. We worked with
Israel and Turkey to overthrow the Assad
government.
And now we've
installed the next generation Osama bin
Laden uh as the leader of this
country. So what do we do? How do how do
we answer, you know, the Antiochian
Orthodox of America when we say, "Sorry,
uh we installed a country or we
installed a government in in the country
and it's going to slaughter your
relatives. It's going to wipe out the
Christian community. It's going to wipe
out the
Alawites. We don't really seem to care.
The Israelis like it, which I don't
understand at all because I always
believe that the devil you know is
better than the devil you don't. The
Israelis jumped in with both feet to
overthrow Assad and have taken what can
only be described now as a buffer zone.
It's an illegal buffer zone. The Syrians
don't seem to
mind. Uh, and the the Israelis love the
fact that the Syrians are now at war
with Lebanon and Hezbollah rather than
being the conduit between Iran and
Lebanon and
Hezbollah. So, I I just I'm not seeing
any good news at all coming out of
Syria. Nothing.
Yeah. As we just saw, we just saw um the
HTS
um men on the ground go after the
Alawites and kill them. And then a week
a week later, HCS's foreign minister,
Syria's foreign minister, uh is um at an
EU conference and they're putting up
money for them and it's like that's
that's interesting. Um I actually uh
spoke to Carl Anslon about this when
everything was going on with HCS and
maybe you'll be to put the the question
to. How do you think Golani went from
this person who went to fight in Iraq
and he was within ISIS rank and then
gets sent to Syria and you know the goal
is you know the long-term goal was the
kind of the to destroy the you know
American Empire and kill Americans to
now being you know at the World Economic
Forum and taking money from the West and
turning a blind eye to Syria to Israel
letting them take land you know channel
4 asked um the Syrian one the Syrian
spokesman, you know, uh, Israel did 500
strikes today. You know, is that is that
an issue? And he's like, we, you know,
basically didn't want to speak. Can I
get your reaction to these Israeli air
strikes? We've had over 300 now.
Our priority is to restore security and
services, to revive civilian life in
institutions, and care for newly
liberated cities. There are many urgent
parts of day-to-day life to restore.
bakeries, electricity, water,
communications. So, our priority is to
provide those services to the people.
I understand it's not your priority, but
are you honestly telling me that you
have nothing to say about Israel
striking 300 sites in this country?
Have no doubt. We want everyone to
respect the sovereignty of the new
Syria. This point is very important to
us. So, do you think there's a chance
that Jolani or could be an asset now,
like a western asset? Like, how how did
he go from that to this? Or is it he
just wants power and that's the way to
get power? I I think he's a very savvy
businessman and I think that he came to
the conclusion early on that it's better
to be friendly with the West than to be
the enemy of the West. And so the very
first thing he did was to invite the
American assistant secretary of state
Barbara Leaf and uh the uh the assistant
secretary of state for hostage affairs
to go to Syria. And this is like days
after he took power. um in exchange for
recognition, the $10 million bounty that
the US had on him was lifted and now
we're all
friends. And so you have the US carrying
his water in places like the the World
Economic Forum or the European Union,
you know, where the US whispers to the
EU leadership, Galani is okay. You can
deal with him. And so now we don't have
to worry about weapons making their way
from Iran through
Syria. It's just not a problem anymore.
And we don't have to worry about a
Russian presence in Syria anymore. You
know, when the when the Russians when
the Russians have to issue a public
statement saying, "We would really
appreciate it if you would respect our
military
bases, you know, they've
lost." And that's exactly what happened.
Do you think that the Trump
administration will change course at
because obviously this happened under
the Biden administration. They
facilitate facilitated HS's rise as in
um on on the march when they overthrew
the government. They provided
intelligence. They got the other rebel
groups to um uh to to work with them and
they coordinated for them. Do you think
Trump will change at all? I mean, JD
Vance put out a few statements where he
was like, you know, how we let these
terrorists take over and going to kill
Christians and and such, but they're so
close to Israel. I mean, see, and that's
the key right
there. Even if Donald Trump cared about
Syria, and I think he
doesn't, I would expect, fully expect
the Israelis to pick up the phone and
say, "Hey, listen. This Syria thing,
back off. We're okay with it." And I
think that's exactly what's happened.
Yeah. I mean, he hasn't really commented
on it at all really. And it's already
done. I mean, and it's only going to uh
help with, you know, with the world
moving more towards China and Russia.
This is a pretty massive win, especially
as you said with the uh you know, Iran
Iranian weapons through Syria into
Lebanon Hezbollah. Um it's it's a huge
win and very unexpected. Um so what what
do you So we start well we started off
kind of the conversation about the
causes of terrorism and that terrorist
group al-Qaeda you know has roots back
to Mujadin against the Soviets in the
80s bin Laden being a financeier there
and he was on I think the independent
newspaper he's a freedom fighter we then
go fight them we talk about all these
different causes um you know does this
just not shine a light on you know I
don't know how people get so freaked out
about you know the the reason for
terrorism they're like it must be this
and then HCS is right there and people
just they don't get the story on it. You
know what what does this mean for
terrorism? You know, well, you know, in
in one respect, it sort of proves that
terrorism
works, right? I mean, you can be a
member of al-Qaeda and then further
radicalize and be a member of ISIS and
dedicate your life to killing Americans
or Brits or other Westerners.
and then take over a country and say,
"Oh, all that stuff I said about
terrorism, I was just being facitious.
We should work together. Hey, can I have
10 billion dollars and some
weapons?" And then that's where we find
ourselves. You know, honestly though,
Louie, to me, this goes to the this goes
to the failure of American policy. Um,
and this goes to the success of of
Turkish foreign policy. The Turks and
the Israelis could not possibly have
played this any better than they did.
And I don't know how it was that the US
was either not paying attention or just
didn't have a policy ready to go where
the Turks moved in and were able to
effect the overthrow of the Assad
government over the course of two weeks
with Israeli pressure in the south. And
the Americans the Americans response was
wait a minute what just happened?
Have you have you not seen there was an
article I think it was in in the
Telegraph I was referring to earlier so
that the US knew about the rebellion in
in advance and I can't remember the
exact name of the group but they said
this is your moment it's either you know
your dream or die basically and they got
them to work with HTS and they had
communication so obviously they was
involved that was the Kurds the the US
has has spawn sponsored over the last 10
or 10 years or so an indep quote unquote
independent um Syrian opposition group,
but most of the money and the material
went to the Kurds and they were working
together, the Kurds and this independent
group. And so when the Turks when the
Americans either were told or realized
that the Turks were moving forward and
they were going to open the the roads to
Damascus, the US jumped in and said,
"Wait, we want a part of this, too." And
I think that's what happened. that that
piece in the independent I think was
100%
correct. Or the Telegraph, not the
Independent. It was in the Telegraph.
Yeah, I have a subscription to the
Telegraph. That's where I saw it.
Yeah. Know, it was an interesting piece
because it was a little bit after
because everyone heard about Turkey
greenlighting it. Um, and I mean this
happened just like days after the
ceasefire between Israel and Hezblah.
Um, which is interesting timing
obviously. But yeah, I just it's just
crazy you have, you know, we we invade
Afghanistan and and Iraq and the rest of
because of 911 and we talk about a safe
haven, right? The safe haven in
Afghanistan, which is why we have to go
after the Taliban. And then instead of
just a pocket of a um a safe haven in a
country, we're like, let's just give
this group a whole country. like, hey,
went from a safe even to, yeah, here's
the government and yeah, come to come to
the World Economic Forum and yeah, the
British, the Germans, the French, we'll
give you some money. And yeah, it's
great. And it shows you how much we hate
Iran and Russia that we would jump into
bed with
al-Qaeda and not just jump into bed with
them, but open doors to the West.
because you know if if they are
attending the World Economic Forum and
opening relations with Western European
or European Union uh countries and
eventually with the United States and
you know by the end of the year we're
going to have an open and operating
embassy into Damascus again.
Um, the idea is going to be to try to
develop the the Syrian economy enough
and westernize them enough so they're
not a threat to Israel. They do what the
Turks tell them to do and not be a
problem for the United States. All the
while keeping the Iranians and the
Russians at bay.
Yeah. I mean, the Russian side of it
interesting. I mean, they've I mean,
they say, "Can we keep our bases?" It
looks like they think they maybe are.
I'm not really sure. I haven't kept
dates. It looks like they're keeping
Latakia, but the other one's closed.
Yeah. And it kind of I mean, there's a
lot of speculation about deals and all
these things. I don't know exactly what
happened, but they seem to kind of just
get on get on with it. And they even put
out, you know, we we need to build
relations with this group because it's
it's happened. So, who who knows what
really happened there, but um just just
Sorry, was you going to say something?
Yeah, I was going to say something. One
of the things that kind of surprised me
and disappointed me was you remember
exactly one week before Assad was
overthrown. It was a Saturday. He and
his family went to Russia and the plane
returned the next day, but only Assad
was on it. His family remained in
Russia. A week later, he went again to
Russia and and never left. Well, in the
week between the first trip and the
second trip, that plane made three more
trips to Russia, and it was just laden
down with cash and artworks and
everything Assad could pack onto the
plane to take with him into
exile. And you would think that in that
week, the Russians would have done
something to try to solidify their
presence in the country, and they didn't
do anything at all.
Yeah, who knows? Maybe maybe some
information will come out. I mean, I
know the UAE would leaning on um Syria
to not be as close with Iran and the US
apparently involved in that. So, I mean,
who knows what goes on behind the scenes
because the UAE had normalized ties with
Assad and they You took the words right
out of my mouth. Yes. Yes. I was gonna
say the exactly the same thing just now.
Yes. Yeah. This was a this was kind of a
well-coordinated uh event. The pressure
got to be so bad that Assad just
couldn't do anything to save himself.
Yeah, it was because I thought, I wonder
what Saudi Arabia and stuff think
because they spent all this money trying
to overthrow him, gave up, normalized
ties, brought him back to the Arab
League, and then he gets overthrown and
then I'm like, I wonder like how they're
going to play it. And then like within a
month uh HTS is foreign ministers
getting a nice warm welcome in Saudi
Arabia in the kingdom. So there you have
your answer. I mean whether they was
like you know we're getting on board
with this. I mean we we tried for years
and someone else did the job for us and
we're reap the fruits of it. That is it.
I I I see it exactly the same way.
And just going to I guess another
general thing within the CIA and
government, you know, we're constantly
told about democracy and we care about
democracy, which is why we care so much
about Ukraine and all these other
places. Um but you know, we see from
World War II onwards constant coups,
constant meddling in governments,
friendly governments, elections,
everything. Um I mean what was the view
inside the CIA about this sort of thing?
I mean, I guess also just on a personal
level, you know, I mean, did you know
this stuff had happened before with
these coups? Did you put it into of the
Cold War? Like, what was your kind of
view then? Oh, sure. Well, what what
you're led to believe when you're a
young recruit
um was, yeah, that stuff all happened,
but it happened before 1975. 1975 was
the Church Committee and the Pike
Committee and the exposure of the family
jewels. We don't do that anymore.
Well, we do do it still, but only when
we really really have to. Only when it's
it's to protect Americans. Okay. Yeah,
we do it all the time.
So, it's it's on a much grander scale
post 1975. it's, you know, invade
Afghanistan, overthrow the Taliban,
which was never a threat to the United
States, by the way, uh, and install a
democracy in a country that has no
history of democracy and has no idea how
to make one work. Um, invade Iraq and
when somebody asks you why you invaded
Iraq, just say something about weapons
of mass destruction and terrorism and
and they'll just forget about it after a
while.
uh we we
we tend to still do it, but rather than
just
encouraging a military coup like we did
in Greece, in Dominican Republic, in
Guatemala and El Salvador, and you know,
some in in Chile, and so many other
places. Now, it's supporting the
fullscale invasion and occupation of a
country, which just simply doesn't work.
And you know, another thing too, and
I've been kind of consistent about this,
is there's always blowback.
Always. And it's like nobody thinks
about the blowback and how damaging this
is going to be. Yeah. I I've told the
story many many times, but the day
before we crossed the border and and
invaded Iraq, uh I was a notetaker in a
principal committee meeting that was
chaired by the vice president. It was
Dick Cheney at the time. And one of the
senior directors from the National
Security Council said, "When we cross
that border tomorrow, they're going to
throw flowers at us." And I said to
George after I said to George Tennant,
the CIA director
afterwards, do they do these people know
nothing about the Middle East? Do they
know nothing about history? And he said,
"No, they
don't." But the CIA's job is to
implement the policy, not to make it. Do
you think they actually believe Do you
think they is that something they even
say to them? Did they actually believe
that? Because you know from the outside
it's always hard not to be more
conspiratorial. Well, but it's group
think. It's group think where everybody
is saying every day Saddam Hussein is so
bad. Saddam Hussein is so evil. Look
what he did. He just he just issued a
presidential proclamation saying that if
you criticize him, you have to have your
tongue cut out and have it nailed to the
front door of your house, which is true.
He did issue a proclamation, but nobody
ever had their tongue cut out. Uh, oh,
he murders everybody he doesn't like.
Uh, he murdered his own brother. He
murdered his own two
sons-in-law. We have to overthrow him.
They're going to throw flowers at us
because we're going to liberate them
from this evil, demonic
uh leader. It's like, actually, no.
They're going to rally against a foreign
invader and
occupier and it's because you guys don't
understand the Arab mindset and you
don't understand the history of the
Middle East.
But people like Donald Rumsfeld was in
he shook his hand. You know, everyone
everyone famous shakes his hand and we
knew they was using chemical weapons on
the Kurds and the Iranians in the Iran
Iraq war. There's documents that
explicitly say we knew and then we even
found out they was coming from Western
Europe and some of them were
subsidiaries of American companies. I
mean, and we backed it and backed it and
backed it and then, you know, we turned
on him when he invades Kuwait. I mean,
it's just so strange, you know, like
Donald Ram shakes his hand, they have
this policy and they're like, "This
guy's evil." And they could have gone
like, "Well, we was using him against
Iran then." But it's like, right. Yeah.
And and the policy at the time, you're
talking about the Reagan administration
during the 1980s. The policy was to
support both Iran and Iraq because we
hated them both and we wanted that war
to last as long as possible so that they
would destroy one
another. It it's it's
scandalous. And that's why when he's
when he's dropping chemical weapons on
the Kurds and and massacring thousands
of innocent civilians and electrifying
the uh the the swamps in southern Iraq
outside Basra and electrocuting, you
know, both fishermen and Iranian troops.
We just said, "Ah, well, that's war.
That's a shame."
Yeah. Yeah. No, no, there definitely was
that, you know, the whole Iran Contra
scandal with playing them off each
other. Whether we preferred Iraq or
Iran, I'm not not particularly sure. But
just just on that, actually, I know
we've only got a few minutes left. Just
I guess with the the war on drugs
question, you know, the Contras, it was
always alleged that um well, the Contras
were using, you know, cocaine sales and
things like that. But you know, how how
involved or not at all do you think the
US government, the CIA was with the
contras and cocaine and and the
speculation that you know, crack in the
80s in the inner city and then, you
know, Ricky Ross, all all that type of
thing. Um, you know, was that as bad as
people think or was it, oh, we knew it
was going on, but we turned a blind eye
because we wanted the Contra to
overthrow the Nicaraguan government and
there was a ban on Congress to to fund
them, which is why we was selling the
weapons through Israel to to Iran. Um,
what do you make of the speculation
about the complicity in in the drug
trade at at that time or beyond as well?
I I think the latter is the truth, you
know, and in in the interest of um
transparency. I was I was the script
adviser on the film Kill the Messenger,
which was about CIA support for the
importation of cocaine from Central
America that found its way to Los
Angeles and launched the crack epidemic.
I believe that was the case. I've never
believed and I don't think that there's
direct evidence that the CIA
um ran the program. I believe that the
CIA facilitated the program, allowed it
to happen, turned a blind eye, and just
said, "Hey, drugs, that's DEA's problem.
It's not our problem. Our problem is we
need to defeat communism in Central
America."
So yeah, when you see when you see shows
like Snowfall for example, which I think
is absolutely
brilliant, just about all of the
storyline there is true.
It Yeah, I think I've heard of the show.
I have to give it a watch. And would you
think it's the same again? Because we
have in the
80s crack. Okay. And then in the early
2000s we have the opioid crisis and that
and then you everyone's seen the graph
in year 2000 Afghanistan opium's down
down we invade go up up and up and up
and again that can just be within the
chaos and there's this guy uh who we
need on our side so we turn a blind eye.
Do you think similar situation again? No
actually I think it's the Chinese that
are pushing um opioids into the United
States. Well it's also big pharma. We
know what big pharma has done to this
country, but uh it's it's the Chinese.
And it's the same thing we did to the
Iranians and the Russians with uh with
heroin poppy from Afghanistan. 93% of
the world's heroin was being produced in
Afghanistan while the US occupied the
country. But all of that heroin went to
Iran and Russia. And we wanted them to
be addicted to heroin because it
weakened their societies. It weakened
their cultures. Well, the Chinese aren't
stupid. They see that our society is
weakened uh with the importation of
opioids and fentinyl and so it's in
Chinese national interests to to push
fentinel across the border. I think
that's what we're seeing
and a a lot of the heroine as well came
from Afghanistan did go to Europe as
well in that in that period. But um yeah
you've given me uh plenty plenty of time
here. I always appreciate speaking to
you. My pleasure. Good to talk to you.
Yeah. Yeah, no, I'd love to have you on
again. Just general discussion. It's
good to to get your get your thoughts.
But um again, thanks for your time and I
recommend people uh watch some of the
recent podcasts you've done. Are you are
you doing a show at the moment with
Colonel um Douglas McGregor about the
JFK files? I saw a clip come up. was is
there something going on there or was
that I I did a I did a an episode of
Piers Morgan's show um on that issue and
I've got a show on a platform called
Unified Television. It's
unifyd television and we we specialize
in these CIA stories, these conspiracy
stories and we try to prove or disprove
um some of the stories and to tell
historical stories based on declassified
CIA documents. So, it's called CIA
declassified and it's at unified TV
unifiD.
Yeah, I'll put that in the show notes in
the screen. I know it's not really a CIA
thing, but did um do you cover at all
anything that's come out about Epste? I
know you've discussed him, Jeffrey
Epste, and your Yeah, we we did an
episode on EP on on Epstein, and I I
sort of laid out the evidence that shows
that he was most likely a Mossad
um a
Mossad agent of access.
Yeah. No, I s I saw that. Um okay. Yeah,
I'll put that all in the show notes.
Again, thank you for your time and uh
have a rest rest of the day. It's nice
and early for you still. Thanks. Nice
and early. I have lots of work to do.
Thanks. Good to talk to you. Thank you.
See you later.